Finding Aid for the Sami Assaad Aintabi Collection of Arabic Manuscripts LSC.0833
UCLA Library Special Collections
- (Kitab) majalis sharifa wa mawa'iz nafisa, 1055 H.; 181; Incomplete pagination. 21 lines.; 20,5 cm. (Box 18)
  Incipit[?]: "al-hamdu lillahi'lladhi rafa'a aqdar al- ulama bi miqdar ma'rifat kitabihi al-mubkam."
  Scribe[?]: Zakariya ibn Adham.
- [No further description available], n.d.; 182/1; 153 leaves. Numbered (rest not numbered). 34 lines.; 20 cm. (Box 18)
- Kiab mi yar (?) al-qudat ala madhhab al-imam al-a zam Abi Hanifa, n.d.; 182/2; No pagination. 18 lines. (Box 9)
  Incipit: "al-hamdu lillah alladhi ja 'ala al- 'ulum ash-shar 'iya mirathan lil- 'ulama."
  Manuscript is incomplete; end is missing.
- [No further description available], 1283 H.; 183; 663 leaves. 26 lines.; 22 cm. (Box 18)
  Incipit: "al-hamdu lillah al-mun'im 'ala l-barr wal-fajir."
  Scribe: Ahmad ibn Darwis*h al-Qassam.
- [No further description available], 1064 H.; 184 (Box 9)
  Incipit: "Hamdan lillah alladhi ja'ala 'l-hamda mannan..."
  Ref: GAL I 405 S I 132, 705.
- Sharh ala kanz ad-daqa iqlil-Imam Abu Hanif, 989 H.; 185; 383 leaves. 19 lines.; 30 cm. (Box 9)
  Incipit: "Bab al-yamin fi-d-darb wal-qatl wa-ghair dhalika."
  Scribe: Muhammad ibn Isma il.
- Risala ... [?], 1146 H.; 186; 10 leaves. 15 lines.; 22 cm. (Box 9)
  Incipit: "al-hamdu lillah alladhi ja'ala al-'ulama warathat al-anbiya wal-mursalin."
  The Risala deals with tafsir.
  Author's Manuscript.
- as-Sifr aih-thani min al-mutashabih fi asma naqalat al-hadith min ar-rijal wan-nisa, n.d.; 187; No pagination. 16 lines.; 19.7 cm. (Box 9)
  Incipit: "Bab Jawa wa-Hawwa fa-Jawwa bil-Jim ibn al-Jawa al-Ansari."
- al-Qaul al-mukhtar fi sharh ghayat al-ikhtiyar, n.d.; 188; 11 fasc., 10 leaves each. 24 lines.; 15 cm. (Box 9)
  Incipit: "al-hamdu lillah tabarrukan bi-fatihat al-kitab."
  Author of Ghayat: Abu Shuja 'al-Isfahani.
  GAL, S.I, 677.
- 'Ilm al-ahkam wash-shara' i', 997 H.; 189; 124 leaves. 17 lines.; 14.5 cm. (Box 9)
  Incipit: "Hamdu man ja 'ala 'l-'ilm ajalla' l mawasib al-haniyya ..."
  A work on fiqh.
- [No further description available], n.d.; 190; No pagination. Number of lines varies.; 21 cm. (Box 9)
  A diwan of poetry.
  Incomplete; at least beginning is missing.
  At least two handwritten manuscripts to be leafed vertically; elaborately ornamented in red, yellow and black ink.
- [2 Titles], n.d.; 191; No pagination. circa. 20 lines.; 21.5 cm. (Box 9)
  1) Nasab al- 'aliama 'ala nusbal-imama.
  2) al-Milal wal-firaq al-islamiya.
  Incipit: "allahumma inni as 'aluka an taghfira li ..."
- [No further description available], 953 H.; 192; No pagination. 13, 15, 19 lines respectively.; 22 cm. (Box 9)
  The volume contains three works of commentary on a text beginning "al-hamdu lillah al-wajib wujuduhu al-mutana naziruhu al-mukin siwahu wa-ghairuhu."
  Three different scribes.
  First work in nastaliq script.
- Kitab al-anwar fi lata if al-akhbar, n.d.; 193; No pagination. 21 lines.; 17.5 cm. (Box 9)
  Incipit: "al-hamdu lillah rabb al-'alamin was-sala5 was salam ala sayyidina Muhammad."
- al- Aqa' id, n.d.; 194; No pagination. 20 lines.; 22 cm. (Box 9)
  Incipit: "al-hamdu lillah al-mutawahhid bi-jalal dhatihi wa-kamal sifatini."
  Scribe: al-Hamawi ash-Shafi' i al-As' ad.
  Ref: For author, S I 754, 950 (?).
- Risala fi fann al-munazara, 1120 H.; 195/2; No pagination. 17 lines.; 21 cm. (Box 9)
  Incipit: "Bi' smi'llah wa-bihemdihi wa-salat Qa-salam 'ala resulihi.. ."
- Risala fi ilm al-adab, 1120 H.; 195/1; No pagination. 17 lines.; 21 cm. (Box 9)
  Incipit: "al-hamdu lillah allachi la mani 'a li- 'ata ihi ..."
  Ref: GAL S II 533 (?).
- Risala 'tafriqiya, 1120 H.; 195/3; No pagination. 17 lines.; 21 cm. (Box 9)
  Incipit: "al-Hamdu lillah alladhi khalage al-Insan allema(hu) el-bayan ..."
  Ref: for author, GAL S II 649.
- al-Hudud al-mukhtara al-musta' mala fi ilm an-nahw[?], n.d.; 196; No pagination. 21 lines.; 19 cm. (Box 9)
  Incipit[?]: "al-Hamdu lillah alladhi a' ta min qadrihi bi' l-'ilm makanan aliyyan. wa-sharrafahu bi' l-lugha al-arabiyya."
- al Mukhtasar ash-shafi 'ala matn al-kafi, n.d.; 197; No pagination. Approximately 23 lines.; 23 cm. (Box 9)
  Incipit: "Hamdun li man sharrafana bi-man huwa sayyid al-kamilin."
  Ref: For author, GAL S II 726.
- Imtihan al-mumtarin al-mutasawwibin (?), 1174 H.; 198; No pagination. Approximately 10 lines.; 23 cm. (Box 9)
  Incipit: "al-hamdu lillah alladhi arsala Muhammad bil-huda wa-din al-haqq ... Amma ba d, fa-qad uridat alaina arida mutadammina ba 'da ayat wa-abyat 'addaha mushkilatan ba' du 'ali al- adhhan."
  A commentary on some difficult verses from the Quran and poetry concentrating mostly on grammatical aspects.
- [No further description available], n.d.; 199; No pagination. 25 lines.; 21.5 cm. (Box 9)
  Incipit[?]: "al-Hamdu lillah allladhi ja 'ala l-ard satira..."
  The qasida deals with sites of the killing and burial of the ahl-al-bait as well as with the Alid imams themselves, their lives and sayings.
  Manuscript incomplete: and missing.
- [No further description available], n.d.; 200; No pagination. 15 lines.; 17.5 cm. (Box 9)
  Incipit: "ala lamma kanat al-hikma aculu hadha shru fi taqassum al-hikma bi-i tiba al-mawcu ila aqsamiha."
  A commentary on a work dealing with the classification of the sciences.
- Ibn al-Ha im, Shihab al-Din Abu l-Abbas Ahmad ibn Muhammad, n.d.; 201/1; 14pp. 23 lines. (Box 9)
  Incipit[?]: "al-Hamdu lillah rabb 'al-alamin was salat was-sa-lam 'ala khair khloihi Muhammad."
  A work on the laws of inheritance (Fara 'id).
  Ref: for author GAL S II 154.
- [No further description available]., 202; No pagination. 23 lines.; 22 cm. (Box 9)
  A work on the laws of inheritance.
  Begining missing.
  Pages not in right order.
- Jawab fi r-radd 'ala man ankara salat ar-ragha' ib, n.d.; 203; 3 leaves. 19 lines.; 17.5 cm. (Box 9)
  Incipit: "Qala al-hajj(?) al-imam al-'alim al 'allama Taqiy al-Din..."
  Manuscript seems to be incomplete.
  Two scribes.
- Diwan, Before 1210 H.; 204; No pagination. 21 lines.; 18 cm. (Box 9)
  Diwan with introduction.
  Glued to binding, a piece of paper carrying the name Muhammad ibn Ali Efendi (Scribe).
- [No further description available], n.d.; 205; 16 leaves. 20 lines.; 25 cm. (Box 9)
  Incipit: "al-hamdu lillah al-maqsud.. ."
- Rauh ar-ruh fima hadatha ba'da'l-mi'a at-tasi'a min al-fitan 'wal-futuh, 1101 H.; 207; No pagination. 9 lines.; 1 9,5 cm. (Box 9)
  Incipit[?]: "Al-hamdu lillahi rabb al-mulk wal-malakut wal-'izza wal-jabarut."
  Ref: GAL II 402 S II 550.
- Raudat al-Funun fi nazm nuqayat al-ulum, n.d.; 210/2; 5pp. 23 lines.; 22 cm. (Box 9)
  Incipit[?]: "al fara'id 'ilm bihi yubhathu 'an maqadir mawarith."
  Manuscript incomplete: only first 5pp.
  Ref: GAL II 368.
- [Removed/Missing from Collection]
  - Risalat i jaza, n.d.; n/a; 10 leaves. 17 lines.; 22 cm.
    Incipit: "al-hamdu lillah hamdu man wasala man inqata's ilaihi bi-ihsanihi."
  - Sharh talkhis fusul Buqrat al-hakim, n.d.; n/a; No pagination. 17 lines.; 16.5 cm.